Guide to the James T. Sears Papers, 1918-2011 and undated, bulk 1950-2004 RL.01162
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James T. Sears papers
1918-2011 and undated, bulk 1950-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sears, James T. (James Thomas), 1951-
RL.01162
138 Linear Feet 317 boxes
Educator, gay rights activist, and author of many works on sexuality, identity, and sex education, and the history of homosexuality and the gay rights movement in the United States. The James T. Sears Papers span the dates 1918-2011, with the bulk of the material covering the period between 1950 and 2004. The papers are arranged into the following series: Audiovisual Material; Other Activities; Personal Papers; Photographic Material; Professional Papers; the largest series, Research and Writings; Jack Nichols Papers; and Oversize Material. The Research and Writings series is divided into subseries for major works by Sears, as well as subseries for other writings and editorial work, research files, and a small set of writings by other individuals. Formats include but are not limited to correspondence, research files, writings, interviews, recordings, serials and newspapers, photographs, and diaries. The collection also houses the personal papers of Hal Call (1917-2000) and Jack Nichols (1938-2005), both early activists for gay rights. Taken as a whole, the collection offers a deep and rich source of information on gay, lesbian, and bisexual culture in the United States, especially in the South, and its representation in literature and in the press, both positive and negative; the history of the gay rights movement in the U.S. and abroad, including the evolution of organizations such as the Mattachine Society and related gay movement publications; sexuality studies in the U.S. and teaching sexuality in primary and secondary classrooms; gays in the military; drag queen, lesbian, and bisexual communities; and many other topics relevant to sexual identity in society.
86,700 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Consent forms signed by individuals whose interviews or images were recorded for possible use in publications are sometimes filed with other records relevant to that publication; oftentimes, however, permissions may have been filed in the Research Permissions Subseries box in the Research and Writings Series, or have not been located in the collection. Researchers wishing to publish information on individuals represented in the Sears Papers must have in hand the consent forms, or obtain permission from the individuals.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials requires production of listening or viewing copies.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James T. Sears Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1996-2012. Additions are expected.
Biographical Note for James Sears
James Sears
1951 Aug. 12 James Thomas Sears born in Tipton, Indiana
1974 Southern Illinois University, B.S. in history, government, and social psychology Indiana University, M.S. in secondary education
1976 Masters of Arts in Political Science, University of Wisconsin-Madison
1983 Anticipating what later came to be known as "queer pedagogy," published Sexuality: Taking off the Masks, in the journal Changing Schools
1983-1984 Trinity University, San Antonio, Visiting Instructor
1984 Doctor of Philosophy in Curriculum Studies and Sociology, Indiana University-Bloomington; thesis analyzed teacher education programs at the University of Indiana
1984-1989 University of South Carolina-Columbia, Assistant Professor
1988 Published first article on gay issues in education, Peering into the Well of Loneliness, in Social Issues and Education
1987-1988 President of the National Curriculum Teachers Network
1988 Founder and first Chairperson of the Lesbian and Gay Studies Special Interest Group of the American Educational Research Association
1988-1991 Received grants from the United States Information Agency
1989-1992 South Carolina Policy Center, Senior Research Associate
1989-1993 University of South Carolina-Columbia, Associate Professor Editor of Empathy: A Magazine of Homophobia Education
1989-1998 Editor, Teaching Education Journal
1990 Published Teaching and Thinking about Curriculum: Critical Inquiries (co-editor)
1991 Publication of Growing up Gay in the South: Race, Gender, and Journeys of the Spirit
1992 Edited Sexuality and the Curriculum: the Politics and Practices of Sexuality Education Lesbian and Gay Educators Award, American Educational Research Association
1993 Received First Amendment Award from the American Civil Liberties Union
1993 Taught controversial course, Christian Fundamentalism and Public Education, University of South Carolina
1993-1994 University of Southern California, Visiting Scholar at the Center for Feminist Research
1993-2004 Professor of Curriculum Studies, University of South Carolina-Columbia
1994-1995 Received grants from the United States Information Agency
1995 Fulbright Senior Scholar, Southeast Asia Association for the Supervision and Curriculum Development Outstanding Research Publication Award
1997 Published Lonely Hunters: an Oral History of Lesbian and Gay Southern Life, 1948-1968 University of Wisconsin-Whitewater, Scholar-in-residence ONE Institute (National Gay and Lesbian Archives), Research Fellow
1999 Publication of A Dangerous Knowing: Sexuality, Pedagogy, and Popular Culture (co-editor) and Queering Elementary Education: Advancing the Dialogue about Sexualities and Schooling (co-editor) Lambda GLSEN (Gay, Lesbian and Straight Education Network) Award for Curriculum, Religion and Public Education
2001 Publication of Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones: Queering Space in the Stonewall South Harvard University, Visiting Professor
2002 Outstanding Academic Book award for Queering Elementary Education
2005-2008 Professor, Penn State University, World Campus
2006 Publication of Behind the Mask of the Mattachine: the Hal Call Chronicles and the Early Movement for Homosexual Emancipation
2009 Publication of Edwin and John: A Southern Gay Couple's Half Century Journey Together Publication of Growing Older: Perspectives on LGBT Aging, a special book-length issue of the Journal of Gay & Lesbian Social Services
Biographical Note for Hal Call
Hal Call
1917 Sept. 20 Harold L. Call born in the state of Missouri
1941-1945 Enlisted in the Army; fought in the Pacific and was awarded the Purple Heart
1947-1952 With a degree in journalism from University of Missouri, entered newspaper publishing business and eventually moved to Chicago to work for the Kansas City Star's office there
1952 Arrested for "lewd acts" in Chicago Moved to San Francisco
1953 Call and others led a what has been described as a takeover of the Mattachine Foundation, ousting founder Harry Hay, and subsequently formed the Mattachine Society
1954 Hal Call and his business partner, Donald Lucas, founded the Pan-Graphic Press, which published the Mattachine Review, the Dorian Book Review, and the Town Talk, one of the first gay publications to contain advertising and to be distributed free in gay bars
1955 Feb. Began publication of the Mattachine Review
1961 Call provided funding and support for the first openly gay man to run for public office in the U.S. - Jose Sarria for San Francisco city supervisor
1964 Call attended and participated in a historic conference and retreat between religious leaders and gay rights activists, in Mill Valley, California; the Council on Religion and the Homosexual (CRH) was created out of this meeting, with Call as one of its leaders
1964 Call and the gay rights movement highlighted in Life magazine and in a CBS documentary by Mike Wallace, first public statement of homosexuality in the U.S. mainstream media
1967 Call gravitated away from Mattachine Society; founded Adonis Bookstore and later, gay video store in San Francisco
2000 Death of Hal Call in Daly City, California at the age of 83
Biographical Note for Jack Nichols
Jack Nichols
1938 Mar. 16 John Richard Nichols born in the state of Washington
1961 Nichols and Dr. Frank Kameny started the Washington chapter of the Mattachine gay rights organization
1967 First gay male to appear in nationally televised interview on CBS to speak openly about homosexuality Jack Nichols gives gay rights speech at Bucknell University, Pa., "Why I Joined the Movement"
1972 Published I Have More Fun With you Than Anybody, early memoir co-authored with Lige Clarke
1997-2004 Edited GayToday.com, an online daily publication
2004 Published The Tomcat Chronicles: Erotic Adventures of a Gay Liberation Pioneer, billed as a gay version of Kerouac's On the Road
2005 May 2 Death of Jack Nichols in Cocoa Beach, Florida
2007 J. Louis Campbell III published Jack Nichols, Gay Pioneer: "Have You Heard My Message?" (Haworth)
Related Material
Atlanta Lesbian Feminist Alliance Archives
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jack Nichols Papers (.6 linear feet)
New York Public Library, Manuscripts Division
Jack Nichols Papers
Pennsylvania State University
Edwin Peacock Papers (Forms part of the Collections on Carson McCullers)
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Julia Penelope Papers
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Minnie Bruce Pratt Papers
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mab Segrest Papers
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dawn Langley Simmons Papers
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Zeigler Papers
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Collection Overview
The James T. Sears Papers span the dates 1918-2008, with the bulk of the material covering the period between 1950 and 2004, and are arranged in the following series: Audiovisual Material; Other Activities; Personal Papers; Photographic Material; Professional Papers; the largest series, Research and Writings; Jack Nichols Papers Series; and Oversize Material, which contains chiefly newspapers and other large-format serials. The Research and Writings series, the largest in the collection, is divided into subseries for each of Sears' major works; in addition, there are other large subseries for Sears' other writings and editorial work, research files, and a small set of writings by other individuals.
The collection documents the career and life of a gay rights activist, educator, and author who has performed ground-breaking research on gay, lesbian, and bisexual culture in the United States, and the teaching of human sexuality in the classroom. The evolution and publication of Sears' major book-length works, articles, and other editorial work is fully documented in this collection in the form of drafts, correspondence, recorded and transcribed oral histories, many research files, and a wide variety of images and recordings. Sears' professional papers contain teaching and course materials as well as files on publicity, speeches, and other activities. Sears also worked as a journal and book editor, thus the collection houses various iterations of authors' accepted work along with Sears' line edits and final publications. Many electronic files accompanied the research, writing, and teaching files; these have been archived on the library's server. An extensive collection of audiovisual materials includes videos, sound recordings, and other media either assembled through Sears' research and teaching activities, or acquired from other sources (note: original recordings are closed to use; unless otherwise noted, listening or viewing copies must be made for research access).
The collection also houses the personal papers of Hal Call (1917-2000) and Jack Nichols (1938-2005), authors and early activists for gay rights. These two large sub-collections contain writings, correspondence, research files, diaries, audiovisual material (separated and removed to the Audiovisual Series), and photographs.
Taken as a whole, the James T. Sears Papers offer a rich source of primary documents and information on gay, lesbian, and bisexual culture in the United States, especially in the South, and its representation in literature and in the press, both positive and negative. The collection also provides extensive documentation on the history of the gay rights movement in the U.S. and abroad, including the evolution of organizations such as the Mattachine Society and related gay movement publications; sexuality studies in the U.S. and teaching sexuality in primary and secondary classrooms; gays in the military; drag queen, lesbian, and bisexual communities; and many other topics relevant to sexual identity in society. The collection also include anthropological field notes of Sears' extensive research and travels in the Philippines related to sexualities and sex education.
Consent forms signed by individuals whose interviews or images were recorded for possible use in publications are sometimes filed with other records relevant to that publication; oftentimes, however, permissions may have been filed in the Research Permissions Subseries box in the Research and Writings Series, or have not been located in the collection. Researchers wishing to publish information on individuals represented in the Sears Papers must have in hand the consent forms, or obtain permission from the individuals.
For more details on the contents and arrangement of individual series or subseries in the Sears Papers, see the series and subseries descriptions that follow.
Separated Material
Books and Other Bound Volumes:
These items have been transferred to the Duke Perkins Library general collections; they can be located through the Duke Libraries online catalog. Arranged alphabetically by author's last name.
Arther, Gavin. The Circle of Sex. San Francisco: Pan-Graphic Press, 1962.
Campbell, J. Louis III. Jack Nichols, Gay Pioneer: "Have you Heard my Message?". Binghampton, NY: Harrington Park Press, 2007.
Kissen, Rita M., ed. Getting Ready for Benjamin: Preparing Teachers for Sexual Diversity in the Classroom. Lanham, Maryland: Rowman and Littlefield Publishers, 2002.
Kumashiro, Kevin K., ed. Troubling Intersections of Race and Sexuality: Queer Students of Color and Anti-Oppressive Education. Lanham, Maryland: Rowman and Littlefield Publishers, 2001.
Lewis, Warfield. Fighting Words: Stories and Cartoons by Members of the Armed Forces of America. New York: J.B. Lippincott Company, 1944.
Lipkin, Arthur. Beyond Diversity Day: A Q and A on Gay and Lesbian Issues in Schools. Lanham, Maryland: Rowman and Littlefield Publishers, 2004.
Macgillivray, Ian K. Sexual Orientation and School Policy: A Practical Guide for Teachers, Administrators, and Community Activists. Lanham, Maryland: Rowman and Littlefield Publishers, 2004.
Mayo, Cris. Disputing the Subject of Sex: Sexuality and Public School Controversies. Lanham, Maryland: Rowman and Littlefield Publishers, 2004.
Sears. James T. Cultural Wars in a Southern Town: Race and the Hidden Narrative of the Master. Educational Policy 14(5): 664-684, 2000.
---. From Margin to Center: On the Other Side of the Curriculum Renaissance. Curriculum Inquiry 33(4):427-440, 2003.
---, ed. Bound by Diversity: Essays, Prose, Photography, and Poetry by Members fo the Lesbian, Bisexual, Gay and Transgender Communities. Columbia, South Carolina: Sebastian Press, 1994.
---, ed. The Greenwood Encyclopedia of Love, Courtship, and Sexuality Through History: The Modern World. Volume 6. Westport, Connecticut: Greenwood Press, 2008.
---. Growing up Gay in the South: Race, Gender and Journeys of the Spirit. New York: Harrington Park Press, 1991.
---, ed. Youth, Education, and Sexualities: An International Encyclopedia. 2 volumes. Westport, Connecticut: Greenwood Press, 2005.
Sears, James T. and J. Dan Marshall, eds. Teaching and Thinking About Curriculum: Critical Inquiries. New York: Teachers College Press, 1990.
Sears, James T. with James C. Carpenter, eds. Curriculum, Religion and Public Education: Conversations for an Enlarging Public Square. New York: Teachers College Press, 1998.
Sloan, Kris and James T. Sears, eds. Democratic Curriculum Theory and Practice: Retrieving Public Spaces. New York: Educator's International Press, 2001.
Zeigler, John. Alaska and Beyond: Selected Poems. Charleston, South Carolina: Tradd Street Press, 1984.
---. The Edwin Poems. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: Xlibris Co., 2007.
Electronic Files:
Thousands of digital files on diskettes and other carriers were found in this collection; they have been separated from the collection and their contents migrated to a library server. The great majority represent drafts of writings by James Sears or Jack Nichols, and images used by Sears in his major works, or assembled by Nichols as part of his personal papers. In general, contributions to works edited by Sears have not been included. Please contact Research Services for assistance in accessing this electronic material.
Gay teenagers -- Southern States; Gays' writings, American; Gay liberation movement -- United States -- History; Gay men -- Southern States; Homosexuality and education; Photographs; Gender identity; Sound recordings; Homophobia -- United States -- History; Homosexuality -- Southern States -- Case studies; Bisexuality -- United States -- History; Philippines -- Social conditions; Lesbians -- United States -- History; Gays -- United States -- Correspondence; Gay activists -- United States; Education -- Curricula -- United States; Gays -- Identity; Oral histories (document genre); Diaries; Video recordings; Electronic media; Film; Southern States -- Social conditions; Sexual minorities -- Education; Sexuality -- Philippines; Religion in the public schools -- United States; Sex instruction -- Curricula -- United States; Slides (photographs); Clarke, Lige; Mattachine Society -- History; Call, Hal, d. 2000; Nichols, Jack; Sears, James T. (James Thomas), 1951-
- Audiovisual Material, 1958-2004 and undated, 40 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  The research conducted by Sears over many decades spawned a large component of audio and visual material, separated from the main collection either as originally received or for preservation purposes, and described in this series. Materials are found in a variety of formats, including audiocassettes, audiotapes, microcassettes, small gauge films, and videocassettes. Subject matter can be grouped into the following categories: interviews with Sears about his career; publicity related to his writings; many oral histories and interviews of Jack Nichols, Hal Call, and other activists and gays individuals interviewed by Sears; histories of regional gay activism in Virginia, Kentucky, and other areas; audio recordings from the earliest programs and conferences on homosexuality in the U.S., some featuring Hal Call and Del Martin as speakers; recordings on aids, cloning, and other issues; classroom and conference lectures by Sears; home movies from James Sears and Jack Nichols; audio recordings belonging in the papers of Jack Nichols; gay parades, rallies, and other social events, filmed by various individuals; and other unidentified recordings.
  Arranged by format (audiocassettes, audiotapes, film, video, and other media), and further subdivided into groupings that, when possible, parallel the series and subseries in the rest of the collection. Format groupings are described in further detail below. Items are arranged within categories mostly in original order as received, with original titles retained.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [RESTRICTION: Originals are closed to use. Use of these materials requires production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Audiocassette Recordings, 1971-2004 and undated
    Each of the audiocassettes boxes holds approximately 20 cassettes. Some recordings are on microcassette and are noted in the container lists below.
    [RESTRICTIONS: Original copies closed to use. Unless otherwise noted, staff must arrange for listening copies to be made. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
    - Jack Nichols Audio Recordings, 1974-2003 Jan.
      Originally part of the Jack Nichols Papers. Chiefly interviews by Nichols and publicity tours taken by Nichols and Lige Clarke. Inidividuals interviewed include Dick Leitsch, Camille Paglia, Dr. George Weinberg, and Randy Wicker. In addition to many radio interviews of Nichols as well as some speeches by him, a number of music recordings are also included. Several recitations of Walt Whitman's poetry by Nichols are this grouping as well. Each of the five boxes holds approximately 20 audiocassettes. Arranged alphabetically and chronologically, in order as received.
      - Cassettes, 1974-2003 (Box 1-5)
    - Audiocassettes from the "Other Activities Series"
      - ScholarLink focus groups and publicity (see Other Activities Series), undated, 5 tapes (Box 5)
    - Professional Papers Series Recordings
      - Conference audiocassettes (AERA, 1996; ASCD, 1990, 1991, 1993), 5 tapes (Box 5)
        Panel discussions on curriculum development and sexuality studies with Sears participating.
      - Teaching materials audiocassettes
        - Moore, Mitzi, teaching, undated (Box 5)
        - Magavern, Kevin, lesson, 1990 Mar. 3 (Box 5)
        - Moore Mitzi, lesson reflections, 1990 Mar. 4 (Box 5)
        - Magavern, Kevin, reflections, 1990 Mar. 5, 2 tapes (Box 5)
        - 825, 1996 Fall (Box 5)
        - Sears, James, curriculum theory class #1, 1998 May 2 (Box 5)
        - Sears, James, talk to N.C. business group [?], Durham, N.C., 1998 Apr. 8 (Box 6)
        - EDLP 825, Sears, 1998 June, 5 tapes, 5 microcassettes (Box 6)
        - Religion symposium, 1998 Apr., 2 tapes (Box 6)
        - GLSEN Talk, Religion Convention and Gays, San Diego, 1998 Apr. (Box 6)
        - Sears, James, Michigan Public Radio, interview by J. Walters, 1995 Oct. 11, duplicate (Box 6)
        - Sears, James et al., Students at Risk: Responding to the Diverse and Unique needs of Gay and Lesbian Youth, ASCD 46th Annual Conference, 1991, duplicate (Box 6)
        - Book interview, undated (Box 6)
        - Curriculum theory Part II, 1998 July 25 (Box 6)
        - Tape 1, 1998 July 11 (Box 6)
        - Tape 2, 1998 July 11 (Box 6)
        - Unmarked tape, undated (Box 6)
        - 1999 Sept. 7-Oct. 18, 5 microcassettes (Box 6)
        - Dr. Monroe, 1998 June, microcassette (Box 6)
        - Unmarked tape, microcassette (Box 6)
        - Sears, This Way Out, interview, Austin, Texas, 2000 May 22 (Box 6)
        - Bauhr, Jane, undated, microcassette (Box 6)
        - Blades, Jane, Rubyfruit Jungle, 2003 Dec., microcassette (Box 6)
        - Cope, Sarah, undated, microcassette (Box 6)
        - D., Nicole and Lydia, undated, microcassette (Box 6)
        - Elise, undated, microcassette (Box 6)
        - Regan, Karen, undated, microcassette (Box 6)
        - Staehr, Tanya, undated, microcassette (Box 6)
        - This side first [otherwise unlabeled], undated, microcassette (Box 6)
        - Putnam, Luella, Left Hand of Darkness, undated (Box 6)
        - Pyatt, Patti, undated (Box 6)
        - Arden and Lane, undated (Box 6)
        - Stec, Blair, Nicole de Villier, undated (Box 6)
        - Dresher, Margaret, undated (Box 6)
        - Smoak, Sarah, A Boy's Own Story, undated (Box 6)